<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Heikki Stark</title>
    <link>https://heke.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Heikki Stark</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 18:28:19 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://heke.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>LogiMech</title>
      <link>https://heke.io/posts/logimech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 18:28:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heke.io/posts/logimech/</guid>
      <description>Prologue Logitech Extreme 3D Pro is a legendary joystick/flightstick, however you want to say it. It was released in 2003 and it is still in production and sold for around 50€. You can get these for cheap. The joystick itself is really basic, but gives you a good variety of buttons and features for a small price. Even if the name gives you a small hint, that there might be a casual version of the joystick, but on the contrary, there isn&amp;rsquo;t.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keyboards by Heikki</title>
      <link>https://heke.io/keyboards/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 17:36:14 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heke.io/keyboards/</guid>
      <description>Browse my previous commission keyboards and find more information on how you can order a custom keyboard!                                KBD67 rev 2.0
      DZ60
      Lily58 Pro
      KBD67 rev 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keyboard portfolio</title>
      <link>https://heke.io/posts/keyboard-portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 20:07:19 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heke.io/posts/keyboard-portfolio/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been gettting a lot of requests and questions about mechanical keyboards. Mostly because of this one video. This one to be exact: Siinä vaiheessa kun @VilleErkkila sanoo, että sillä on hyvä idea, ei voi vaan kieltäytyä. Hymyilen ääneen tätä meidän pientä projektia 😂 #kiehucreative #mechkeebs https://t.co/bHgIcgo6nj
&amp;mdash; Heikki Stark (@heikkistark) April 30, 2020  For this video, I want to give a short shoutout to Ville Erkkilä and Kiehu Creative for coming up with the idea and filming the amazing video.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://heke.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 15:58:45 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://heke.io/about/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s a me, Heikki!
  My name is Heikki and I live in Finland. I am currently working as a information security specialist at F-Secure, but during my free time I am part of a hacking team called LeftOvers. You can see me in multiple InfoSec related communities. If you happen to see me, please come say hi!
In October 2020, I decided to start doing mechanical keyboard stuff (assemblying and fixing etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>